[SPEAKER_01]: You see me as a backdrop?
[SPEAKER_00]: I was wondering if you could describe nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is that?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is your aim?
[SPEAKER_00]: Your aim is nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: You mean if somebody gives that as an answer to a question?
[SPEAKER_01]: But, you know, my aim is nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's the thing, actually.
[SPEAKER_01]: Understanding correctly what nibbāna is, means you would be at least a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fully developing that understanding means, yeah, you have now developed nibbāna, as in became an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: As to what it is, well, as the suttas would describe it, it's absence of greed, aversion and delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Complete absence, in the sense of the possibility of greed, aversion or delusion is impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: So the mind has fully understood it and fully got rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not a place that one goes to.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: It isn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not... it's not a... it's not a magical realm that kind of gets... one enters upon if... upon some certain practice of a special meditation technique or something like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not a place you go into and replace what you know with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's really what you know now, your experience as it is, what you have now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Remove greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Remove possibility of greed, possibility of aversion, possibility of delusion from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what nibbāna becomes.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what nibbāna is.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why we would say cooling down, literally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Cooling down of the fires of passion, anger and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you cool, cool this thing down, this experience, this life you have, you cool it down to the point of being irreversible.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot go back and be entered again by greed, aversion or delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's been fully, fully frozen to the point of these three things dying out and now they cannot reappear.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's, that's, that's a developed nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can see that in order to cool something down,
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to have it, you need to acknowledge it, you need to admit it, you need to see where the work in cooling it down lies.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not replacing it with some new world, a new realm, or new meditation experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're actually fully understanding what you already have.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you don't need anything new.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever it's necessary for nibbāna, you already have it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everybody already has it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Buddha would refer to it as an element of nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: In everyone's experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in possibility of developing the phenomenon which is nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: That means, element of nibbāna is present.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not about belief.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, you see, when people took it as a belief, that's when they started saying, well, we are already in nibbāna, because nibbāna is already there.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's when you fail to see the difference between the possibility and, like, actual development of something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, nibbāna is there as a possibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: But,
[SPEAKER_01]: Saying that you have developed nibbāna means you need to have it as your actual experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, you need to do the work of getting rid of greed, aversion, delusion, ill-will, hatred, sensuality, all of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, nibbāna is the perfected human being, and it's a perfected...
[SPEAKER_01]: Pretty much, but then, see, perfected human being, basically, it's certainly a perfection, but you wouldn't refer to that person as a human being anymore, because human,
[SPEAKER_01]: It means going with the nature, going with the grain, going with the current, going with desires, going with the cravings and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what makes humans human.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you actually... you cease to be human.
[SPEAKER_01]: Arahant is not human anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: If that's the designation you would use for a human.
[SPEAKER_01]: But yeah, overall, sure, as an individual, he still partakes as a being in the human realm.
[SPEAKER_01]: But really, what makes human human are these things that you sort of undo and relinquish as an arahant, as somebody who is enlightened.
[SPEAKER_00]: Overcoming your humanity.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, pretty much, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: First, you need to overcome the immorality and non-virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, you need to overcome that as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you're not really measurable by any human standards.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's not like a good human or a bad human, a good person or a bad... No, he's not a person anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's done.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's abandoned, relinquished the ownership of the slightest sort of appropriation of his own senses, his own aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nibbāna is also called the non... what?
[SPEAKER_00]: Non-appropriation in English, in other...
[SPEAKER_01]: Right, yeah, yeah, yeah, sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Non-appropriation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or the undetermined.
[SPEAKER_01]: The undetermined, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the things that are determined for a human, for an unenlightened, unenlightened being, are things that are determined by greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you remove that and there is nothing determining things as mine anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, that experience is the undetermined.
[SPEAKER_01]: The experience of the undetermined.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's a real experience as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why nibbāna is a thing, a phenomena, a dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't really show people that nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Can you show them nibbāna?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, of course not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you can guide them to it, but even that will not necessarily result in them getting to it, unless they have made the effort themselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can point at it, you can describe it, you can lay out the way that somebody can practice towards it, but unless they practice...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like getting real, getting absolutely real.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Being honest with your situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's up to me, it's not... Oh, yeah, absolutely, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, not just being... like being honest with the situation, but also recognizing...
[SPEAKER_01]: The Buddha would refer to it as measure the task.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like a person would go and listen to like a... whatever, somebody he deems wise, somebody he deems that he can help him.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then he would ponder on the meaning of what's being said and what needs to be done.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once he starts grasping the meaning, he can see, oh, okay, this is...
[SPEAKER_01]: The amount of effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is what I need to do to, like, measure the task.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is absolutely necessary in order to be able to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But most people don't... they kind of omit that whole thing of, hold on, what does this actually mean?
[SPEAKER_01]: It might make me feel good.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's my making me... it's my... it's... it might be very inspiring for me, but do I understand what it means?
[SPEAKER_01]: When I read the suttas or when I face instruction that's sort of directing me towards nibbāna, am I aware of... of... of the actual
[SPEAKER_01]: Meaning of it, as in, like, what exactly I need to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: And most people are not encouraged to think like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's most like, okay, you're inspired, that's great.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, here is a meditation technique that you just do mechanically, and then the experience you have, if it's substantial enough, as in, like, if it affects you significantly enough, then we can interpret it as nibbāna, or as something leading to nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: But nibbāna is not an interpretation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any, basically, any part of developing wisdom does not partake in interpretation, certainly not by external terms.
[SPEAKER_01]: It partakes in direct understanding of the meaning of it, which then results in direct freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: And hence, that's the greatest verification of your wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know you're right, because you cannot suffer amidst suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot engage in your will.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot engage in sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot engage in craving, or distraction, or delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even if the whole world says, no, that's wrong, you know that they're wrong, because you are the one free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why arahant, anāgāmī, sakadāgāmī, sotāpanna, basically, dead ones, they go... Well, arahant is completely developed against the grain.
[SPEAKER_01]: against the grain of nature and the outputs of the mind and intentions and cravings and feelings and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sotāpanna is somebody who got... he understood it.
[SPEAKER_01]: He understood what that is, but he hasn't fully developed it.
[SPEAKER_01]: He hasn't fully went upstream, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, as I said, it's not like a theory or ideology that you're sort of...
[SPEAKER_01]: Justifying and making it like an argument proof or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's a directly verifiable in your experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you have the criteria.
[SPEAKER_01]: Suffering and freedom from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sensuality and freedom from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ill will and freedom from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're free from those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not because you've been running away from those things, or you've been hiding, or sort of trying to manage the circumstances, so you don't get challenged externally.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're free from those things, because amidst those things, the mind cannot be overwhelmed by them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't engage.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not even a matter of restraint anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: It becomes impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once understanding has fully taken place, it becomes impossible to suffer amid suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, as I said, that that is the the greatest verification a person can have, that they've been practicing rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no verification from others?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, of course not.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well done.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, the others can verify it as they did in the suttas, basically, not by, yes, I see the magic blue light aura around his head, he's an arahant, but by talking to that person, interrogating them, to the point of discerning the subtle meanings, and they were like, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because an arahant would know what another arahant needs, has to have understood beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he would know that, which means, through questioning, he could see the extent of other person's understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's... that's... that was also a way of progress as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Buddha would often encourage that in the suttas, saying the monks would sort of interrogate each other, not like for the sake of argument, but for the sake of pressing for the meaning.
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't leave anything unturned.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you'll be drilling and delving and basically making effort to understand and then being questioned by your... what's the translation?...
[SPEAKER_01]: by spiritual companions and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, it's like, have you understood this?
[SPEAKER_01]: Have you understood?
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you thought you did, well, you will then be able to convey it to somebody else who did understand it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, again, if you thought you did, but you haven't, this questioning can actually spur you to make further effort, because you realize, oh, okay, I haven't been considering this, or that, or whatever the questions contain.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, again, you can see that most of the modern practice today, when it comes to Buddhism meditation, has nothing to do with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just watch your nostrils, cross your legs, sit in lotus, and that's it, and it will happen, whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: From what you just said, it seems that discussing the dhamma is useful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Go on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Shall I continue the sentence?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Discussing the dhamma is useful, provided that at least one of those people has understood it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Otherwise, it's blind leading the blind.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, two unenlightened persons, people who haven't even understood what sotāpati is, they can discuss the dhamma all they want.
[SPEAKER_01]: It won't result in knowledge.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, like, you pair two ignorances together, it's not going to amount to knowledge.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because Putujan's experience is top-to-bottom ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you cannot accidentally stumble upon or even find a right reference towards that ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Buddha said, the absolutely necessary condition for arising on the right view is utterance of another, of another who has understood it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, paired with that, they need to have the right attention.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, they need to know, basically, how to hear it, not to dismiss it, how to attend to it, and how to practice that right utterance.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, once... See, like, for example, two sotāpānas could enable each other better in practice, if they were to discuss it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it would just be reminding them of what they already know, but they haven't pressed it far enough, in terms of understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or even better, sotāpaṭṭhāna talking to an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: But putujana toitu putujana, it can only remain putujana.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or be dealing with mundane terms.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: It might be helping each other how to manage their suffering better.
[SPEAKER_01]: But sotāpaṭṭhāna is not management of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the first step of uprooting it.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, you know exactly how to uproot it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's already freedom from suffering, you know, to a great degree.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what about speech?
[SPEAKER_00]: Truthful speech?
[SPEAKER_00]: Right speech?
[SPEAKER_00]: Would you say, so you wouldn't say that discussing the dhamma or your concerns, your spiritual concerns, with other people who are also on the same kind of path, you wouldn't say that's right or noble?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, if you define noble by that which pertains to, like, sort of your higher, then it isn't, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, it can help people because
[SPEAKER_01]: In a sense of, eh... it can... it can make them make the effort on the personal level further by having an intelligent feedback, even if it's unadvertentional.
[SPEAKER_01]: What they should not expect is that the conversation, the discussion itself, results in some great epiphany.
[SPEAKER_01]: But in the same sense, you come across a new sutta, or you come across other wrong view, that then you actually understand better, and by doing so, you clarify what the right view is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, of course, that's all thanks to their personal effort towards understanding the nature of suffering and freedom from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, yes, if there is... if the other person is equally sort of striving as you are, then that discussion can sort of just, well, at least hint at certain directions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of your reflection and of your contemplation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Good.
[SPEAKER_00]: Both of those people say, well, I'm not enlightened.
[SPEAKER_00]: Are you enlightened?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, I'm not enlightened.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's two unenlightened, honest unenlightened.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, now, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is a difference between that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have sometimes people debating just because it's pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, let's have a discussion about it and just bounce ideas off each other.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I mean, that's utterly pointless.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you know your situation, that you're a putugena, you know that nothing sort of supramundane, so to speak, can come out of this discussion with another putugena, but you do it just to highlight your ignorance further, which means you did begin with that self-honest attitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: But in that same sense, you don't even need the other person.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just pick up any philosophy book and look at like, okay, this is supposedly the wrong view.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, have I understood it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: And to what extent?
[SPEAKER_01]: And where exactly it's wrong?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by then...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're not looking for faults.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're genuinely adopting that view in order to be able to understand the extent of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by doing so... That's why often the Buddha would describe all these wrong views that were present at the time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because by fully understanding their extent, one would be much closer to the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as I said, discussing with another equally intelligent, equally self-transparent person, that can help.
[SPEAKER_01]: Stop making noise.
[SPEAKER_01]: That can help.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, reading other books or other teachings can help.
[SPEAKER_01]: But not if you don't have that necessary self-transparent basis.
[SPEAKER_00]: Come here.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, ideally, you want to be discussing these things with a sotāpanna, someone who has...
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, then you can... yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because otherwise, I think it is just stabbing in the dark.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even if you actually do...
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you do actually stab something, you wouldn't know it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, hey, you can profit from it if you're already very self-transparent.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, you would profit from reading other views, other things, because you do have self-transparency.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're not looking for faults, you're not covering it up, you haven't just adopted the belief that this is wrong, but you're genuinely understanding the extent of it, and why it's wrong, and how it's wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, for a person who wants to discuss with a sotāpanna,
[SPEAKER_00]: How can he find one?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: He has no reference.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is his criteria?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, this is what his criteria is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the closest to the right criteria he can get is this self-transparency, being honest with oneself, and not being dismissive of other views, even if they are not pleasing to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, usually, people's criteria for their views, opinions, ideologies, beliefs, is basically emotional.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is pleasing to me for whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is maybe a small kind of degree of reasoning involved, but mostly it's just this is emotionally pleasing to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, this is my view and that's why I'm defending it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why I'm criticizing other views.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not because I have understood my view or I've understood other views.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just because, circumstantially, I adopted it and now I'm defending it at all cost.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that attitude is basically the main impediment.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's like the wrong attention.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddha said that looking for faults in a speaker will prevent you understanding what he means.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by not getting the meaning, then you might actually, sort of, cross over a sotāpanna, or even an arahant, who's been speaking, you've been listening to it, but you were not paying proper attention, as in you were dismissing it, or not listening to it carefully enough, and that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: And your views, your wrong views, your wrong criterias remained unaffected.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means you're none the wiser.
[SPEAKER_01]: None the wiser even by, like, having a Buddha himself in front of you, teaching you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're self-transparent, honest with yourself, so you know your situation, you know that you're not free from suffering, not free from sensuality or greed or aversion, and then you also recognize the inevitability of having to have some views.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you don't judge... you don't judge your situation through your views, you judge your views through a situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, you can't help having views, but at the same time you recognize, well, I'm not free from suffering, I'm not free from greed, aversion, delusion, I'm not a sotāpanna, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, the views that I do hold and regard dear, I should put in question.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's because of those very views, that I'm not free from suffering, free from greed, aversion, delusion, I'm not a sotāpanna yet.
[SPEAKER_01]: But people might think one thing, then they might think about the second thing of their views, but they'll never put it together and see that that's a contradiction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you can't have puthujjana's views that are right and not be a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because right view means sotāpatti.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you don't have the right view, you can't then entertain the notion that you're puttu...
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry, if you're not a puthujjana, if you're not a sotāpanna, if you're a puthujjana, you can't entertain a notion that you also have right views.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that attitude is unpleasant, because it's like living in perpetual doubt of your own existence.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's... that's very... can be very anxious, very... yeah, full... like lot... quite... lots of... lots of sort of concern, because any single view that then you... you look into, you realize, well, this might be wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then any confidence that you might have had as a Bhutujana gets completely undone, demolished.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why when the practice of dhamma, when thinking and reflecting upon views, it's not optional anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's existential, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to clarify it, because you realize the peril of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't just simply adopt a belief that... Well, you can adopt a belief, but if you are self-honest, if you do have that honesty, you wouldn't be able to.
[SPEAKER_01]: As appealing as a belief might be, you wouldn't be able to, eh... Well, you would be able to at the expense of honest, self-honesty.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you realize that self-honesty should not be compromised ever, then, eh... that's your safeguard against adopting and proliferating things just simply upon a belief.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, if you adopt something, it would be after heavy scrutiny.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even then, you wouldn't adopt it as a belief.
[SPEAKER_01]: You would adopt it pretty much as a strategy towards your practice of freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, if that strategy is not bearing any fruit, and you're not free from suffering, you're going to be upgrading it or changing it, and you won't be afraid to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And faith... Well, that's... See, you can have...
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't have a belief without faith, but you can have faith without a belief.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the faith that we are talking about is the... is the...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think it's in the sutras it's mentioned, and I might have spoken about it before.
[SPEAKER_01]: The faith we are talking about is the faith that you would have, that a person would have in a doctor.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, you recognize your situation through that self-honest scrutiny of yourself, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: You recognize that you need help, as in, you are a subject to suffering, you are prey to suffering,
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't know the way out from a reasoned suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you find something that promises a way out.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you have faith that it might work.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's applied, obviously.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in the same sense, you recognize you have an illness, you go to a doctor, so you have faith that he can help you, that he can prescribe you medicine, and whatever, a course of treatment or something, that will then result in that freedom.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, from that ailment.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you do start taking medicine and doing everything rightly, you understood doctor's instructions properly, and you're not being free from your ailment, well, maybe
[SPEAKER_01]: Faith a bit longer, a bit more, keep applying it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, if it's nothing, there's no results, well, then you won't have a problem changing it, looking for a different way, because it's not working.
[SPEAKER_01]: You haven't done it out of a sort of emotional attitude, or you... nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you really... you genuinely tried, and it didn't free you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if it does free you, then that faith disappears, because you have... you don't have to have faith that it will work, because now you know that it worked, and you are cured.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why in the suttas, like for Sotāpanna, his faith in the Buddha, dhamma, saṅgha has been replaced by the confirmed confidence.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it was confirmed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now he can see, he can see his health as a direct result of having faith in this application.
[SPEAKER_01]: But again, you need to be honest, because if you're not, you're going to be blaming a doctor.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're going to be blaming the one who gave the instruction.
[SPEAKER_01]: But actually, you first need to start with yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if it's not working, if you don't have patience, if it's not working quickly... Well, if you don't have patience and you're not self-transparent, you won't see that you're impatient.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, you won't see that it's actually your lack of patience that's a problem, as in you need to take the medicine a bit longer.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you're just going to dismiss the doctor, who could have been Buddha himself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why I insist always on, like, self-transparency, because if you're not, you will be pointing fingers, basically, when there are no results to show for.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the instructions given by the Buddha... What are they?
[SPEAKER_00]: What was his first instructions?
[SPEAKER_00]: What was his first thing to do?
[SPEAKER_01]: There's suffering, there's freedom from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you have to... By the way, are you recording?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Buddha only gives precepts much later on in his... during his life, much later on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, he defines them specifically later on, but the the actual virtue that was sort of contained in the eight precepts has been praised by him throughout the suttas, in Digha, Inca, Majjhima, Inca.
[SPEAKER_01]: He would say that the wise men of the past were virtuous, and so he was just... he was taking for granted, basically, that somebody who has already came to that point of practicing the dhamma has already had their virtue developed.
[SPEAKER_01]: They've been restrained, moral, virtuous, honest, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Where did they get those... that morality from?
[SPEAKER_00]: Who?
[SPEAKER_00]: The people who...
[SPEAKER_01]: In the past?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, from understanding the natural principles, as in the universal principles of a human existence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, understanding principles... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Say, if you... Basically, if you understand why is virtue virtues, it's already the beginning of wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can also arrive at that understanding by taking virtue and faith, the faith we discussed.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have faith that virtue is necessary.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, the doctor says, tells you, well, this medicine will work,
[SPEAKER_01]: Only if you follow a strict diet.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're careless with what you eat, it's going to cancel the effectiveness of a prescription I'm giving you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But obviously, some people will not have even that little bit of faith.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if they do investigate, reflect upon themselves in that same transparent manner, well, you would see basically that virtue is virtuous because it does not contain any existential discrepancy or contradiction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, in order to arrive at it, you are already developing wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, good things are good because they're basically aligned with the universal principles, with things that are most fundamental.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, for example,
[SPEAKER_01]: Sharing and giving and charity is good.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, people say, oh, it makes me feel good.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all secondary.
[SPEAKER_01]: Existentially, charity is good, because it goes along the way of you not being owner of the things in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, everybody starts with the sense of ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's completely gratuitous, but everybody owns.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everybody immediately feels they're the owner of their body, their senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, through engagement with the world, through the tools, which are your senses, which is your body, you start... you're fully identified with the tools.
[SPEAKER_01]: With eye, nose, ears, and mouth, body, and everything else, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't know why, but they said giving is good.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, giving is good, because you basically deprive yourself of something to give to somebody else, which resembles the experience of non-ownership of that which has been owned.
[SPEAKER_01]: That which I still regard as mine, I give to somebody else.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can arrive at it either through doing that, and then contemplating it, or not doing it, but then you need to have discernment.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's highly unlikely you're going to arrive at it through stinginess and, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: And complete sort of lack of any virtue, basis of virtue, or charity and kindness.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can take any other thing that's regarded as good and virtuous, genuinely, you would see that it would be along the... it would be mirroring, it would be reflecting upon some principles of your existence, that you're living right there and then, but you're not aware of.
[SPEAKER_01]: Lying, basically, it's another discrepancy.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is a truth.
[SPEAKER_01]: You choose to override it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You choose to act upon that discrepancy and then perpetuate it as a non-discrepancy.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why it's unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Same stealing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It reinforces that perverted pattern of human existence.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, I am the owner of my body and my senses and things that I can gain through.
[SPEAKER_01]: To the point of then taking that which you perceive through your senses as not yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: As an extension of the very attitude that you have towards your own senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because basically, you do become a thief.
[SPEAKER_01]: We might have all started as... as borrowing.
[SPEAKER_01]: We're all just... just... just basically renting this body and these senses, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're given to us for our use.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the moment you start regarding as yours, that which you have rented, you have effectively stolen.
[SPEAKER_00]: Taken from Mara.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, the Buddha did say that.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, because people take and use that which doesn't belong to them, well, they take it as theirs, that which doesn't belong to them, that's why the Mahārāja controls them and does what he wants and that's why they're subject to suffering and the whole...
[SPEAKER_01]: Death and misery and everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, when the monks asked, what are those things?
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, it's eyes and objects, ears and sounds, nose and smells, mouth, sorry, tongue and tastes, body and touches.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those are the things, basically, that don't belong to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're just renting.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're just borrowed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Borrowed jewelry, as the Buddha would refer to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you start entertaining the notion that you are their owner, they are their own.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's not like a metaphysical secret that you need to figure out in order to drop it, to not regard it as yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you just need to dwell on the fact that they're not yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just need to keep really, really, really investigating the meaning of not mine and then applying it to yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, obviously, in the most general terms, that's what the Buddha would describe, like, well, if you were the owner of your body, for example, would that body be subjected to sickness, aging and death?
[SPEAKER_01]: It wouldn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, many people think that, oh, yeah, of course, I understand that, I'm subject to all these things.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you truly understood... if you were to truly understand that, you would be completely free from appropriation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're self-transparent, then you would see a discrepancy.
[SPEAKER_01]: On one hand, I'm thinking I understood it.
[SPEAKER_01]: On another hand, I don't have that which is supposed to be the result of that understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, freedom from appropriation, freedom from suffering, freedom from greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you see that discrepancy, that contradiction, then you'll know exactly where to do the work.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is, okay, I need to understand this further.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what I think understanding is, it's not sufficient.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or sometimes it's just plain-out wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you haven't... you wouldn't have seen it unless you brought this discrepancy, like, to the fore and fully understood it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, initially, one takes on virtue given from an external...
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Set of values, or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you could see that in every society there is a degree of it, because it would kind of seep down into, like, you know, collective society awareness, that's sort of among the, like, completely unenlightened people, but you still get the sense of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sharing is good, patience is good, all these things.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is good, but it's also good to understand why these things are good.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because then you can take it even further.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, yeah, you can discover virtue by yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I suppose.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the Buddha did.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you could say that the Buddha did discover it by himself.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's highly unlikely, because you would kind of need some pointers, some external reference point.
[SPEAKER_01]: You would go a bit deeper without having... Well, you can only take it so far, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: You could discover virtue by yourself, to a degree, but not fully understand it to the point of becoming a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in the one who has understood sīla, and thus he's free from sīla-bhāta-paramāsa, which is virtue and duty.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fetter of virtue and duty he's free from.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's another thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: In order to understand virtue, you need to have it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't be a non-virtuous person and then understand the nature of virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to be having it present in your presently arisen experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, you need to be virtuous, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: But being virtues in itself, it's nice, but it does not result in wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if there's no wisdom, there's no liberation.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why, obviously, sīla and virtue, it's not the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's why also dhamma is impossible to arise without sīla.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because how can you understand... how can you develop understanding of sīla without sīla?
[SPEAKER_01]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: But many people don't see that connection, which is why that is the very first fetter of sīla bhātta-paramāsa.
[SPEAKER_01]: People think you must be virtuous, and yes, you do.
[SPEAKER_01]: You do have to be virtuous.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then they think, okay, so I'm doing that, and now the practice of dhamma and understanding is over here.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm doing my meditation technique, I'm reading the suttas, I'm studying Pali, and I'm virtuous.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's all contributing.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, you have the virtue, you have the morality, you have the restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: You take it then further and practice, like, the sensory strength even of things that are not necessarily non-virtuous, but are not virtuous enough, perhaps.
[SPEAKER_01]: Such as pursuing sight, sound, smell, taste, touches that are distracting.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're not necessarily rooted in anger and breaking of moral precepts or rooted in sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: And breaking celibacy, precepts and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they can be rooted in distraction and carelessness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you stop doing that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you understand that very basis.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need to go elsewhere.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need some other, like, whatever, developing of some sort of, ah, sapra mundane concentration.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You already have it in front of you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, you need to start making the effort to cut through that fog of ignorance in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't just take it for granted that it's good.
[SPEAKER_01]: Understand it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why it is good.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the definition of sotāpanna is he's the one who knows good as good and bad as bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: Putujana is like a virtuous putujana.
[SPEAKER_01]: A good putujana is the one who doesn't know good as good, bad as bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you do want to practice meditation and contemplation, practice it within the basis of your virtuous behavior and sensory strength.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not left, right, before or after it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Within it.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, when this, this is.
[SPEAKER_01]: When the basis of virtue is present, me trying to understand it is also present.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the point is to understand that they're not found elsewhere or they're not given to you through some sort of divine providence, through some sort of super concentration you developed and then you have this great revelation.
[SPEAKER_01]: You develop it on the basis that you maintain.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're maintaining the basis of virtue, and then you develop your understanding of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why for Sotāpanna, who has understood the nature of virtue, who has understood good is good, bad is bad, all he needs to do is continue practicing nekama-saṅkhapa, as in the video we described it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thoughts of renunciation, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, being virtuous and sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, through doing it, he's developing that very understanding of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you would also, as the Buddha would often encourage people, to see the danger in the slightest fault.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you would start seeing the danger in the slightest fault.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or it's just a small thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Big thing or small thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it partakes in the nature of unwholesome, it's unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, it's directly against the principle of dhamma, the universal principles.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why it would be enough for somebody to receive instruction as simple as avoid anything that's unwholesome and cultivate anything that's wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: As they did in the suttas, the the Buddha's foster mother, when she asked for that instruction, and the Buddha said, like, anything you know, it's unwholesome, abandon it, and anything you know, it's wholesome, cultivate.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then she went for, like, seclusion for three months and so on, and came back, an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fully enlightened.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fully freed, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because she fully understood it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you could see how many people today... oh, yeah, of course, this is bad, this is good.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you were to truly understand that, you'd be at least Sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, if you think you have a knowledge of what's good, what's bad, ask yourself, are you Sotāpanna?
[SPEAKER_01]: Are you a stream-enterer?
[SPEAKER_01]: If the answer is no, then don't take that knowledge for granted, because it's not sufficient.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, it might be good and sufficient for mundane terms,
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's... well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you might be, means you're not free from another fetter, which is in that first group, which is fetter of doubt.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't know you're a sotāpanna, means you're not sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Understanding what sotāpanna is, makes you one.
[SPEAKER_01]: Understanding what sīlabhātparamāsa is, frees you from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Understanding what a self-view is,
[SPEAKER_01]: It frees you from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't say, I might be free from self-view, but I don't know it yet.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means you're not.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mentioned yesterday, when I was talking to those people, eh... with...
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't want to mention names, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, this whole, like, self-reflexive attitude is, like, you really want to do it in order to gain wisdom, to learn from it, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't want to be... You're not doing it because you want to justify your actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, that's how people usually be doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not gonna say it again.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ciao.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you really want to ask yourself, basically, like, say, when it comes to practice of dhamma, why are you doing it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, really clarify.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where do you want to arrive with it?
[SPEAKER_01]: What's the goal?
[SPEAKER_01]: And just... or in general, in any areas of your life, basically, just ask yourself, what do I want to do with my life?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is my purpose?
[SPEAKER_01]: But don't ask and expect immediate answer or something like that, but ask and then think about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, if the answer presents itself, well, then question that answer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because most people would be...
[SPEAKER_01]: We'd be going through life, basically, like...
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know if there's an English expression, but certainly back in Serbia, like a headless fly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Headless chicken.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you know, like a fly that doesn't have... and it's just flying like mad, left and right, hitting into windows.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still flying, but it doesn't have the head, so it doesn't see where anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: And most people would actually be able to help themselves if they just stop for a second and ask yourself, like, why am I doing this particular thing?
[SPEAKER_01]: What for?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why do I want it?
[SPEAKER_01]: What do I want?
[SPEAKER_01]: Most people don't even know what they want.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're just like habitually scratching the itch, like an animal, basically, and going through things as they arise.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the attitude would help even in terms of like an ordinary lay life, somebody who's not interested in greater development of the dhamma or so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: But let alone for somebody who does want to practice dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just completely necessary.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to develop that self-reflection, that transparency and that kind of scrutiny of your own self, of your own thoughts, of your own intentions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it will force the correct perspective upon you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't have it willingly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't just willingly adopt the correct perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because any perspective you know of, it's already perspective that's affected by greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, just ask yourself, where do I want to be?
[SPEAKER_01]: And say, in one year time, or two years time, provided I live that long.
[SPEAKER_01]: What's my purpose?
[SPEAKER_01]: What's my goal?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, like, you can basically review things that you already got committed to or engaged, and it's just like, well, why am I doing this?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why am I still doing this?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why did I start doing this?
[SPEAKER_01]: And see where the answers come up.
[SPEAKER_00]: You won't be successful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, so what for?
[SPEAKER_01]: Say, I'm doing this job because I want to earn money and be my own boss.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is that a good thing, being your own boss?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is that something you value?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the answer would be because it's unpleasant to have somebody else telling me what to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, so why is then the unpleasant experience of having somebody else tell you what to do, why is that a problem for you on the personal level?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why can't you just remain indifferent towards the equanimous?
[SPEAKER_01]: And just do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is it a problem?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's a problem because it's making me suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah, so suffering is a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: So now, you're doing this job, ten hours a day, earning loads of money, trying to study, just because you don't... so you don't suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, is there a guarantee that you won't suffer after all that effort you put in?
[SPEAKER_01]: There isn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, secondly,
[SPEAKER_01]: That all effort you put in, you might have overcome possibility of suffering on account of somebody else telling you what to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, there're millions of other ways of suffering in your life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, you invested your... like, your whole life, how many years of building something up, just to address like 0.1% of possibilities of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: You haven't freed yourself from the nature of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: You've only freed yourself from one particular manifestation of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Having somebody else, less qualified than me, telling me what to do and bossing me around.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is that a... is that a fair investment?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is that a good investment?
[SPEAKER_01]: You realize it isn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, obviously, the inevitable question is, well, what do I do then?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you ask yourself, what's more important?
[SPEAKER_01]: Being completely free from suffering, or partially.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, you can choose whatever you want, but choose... then you will choose it... choose it responsibly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because now you know, okay, there is a possibility of being free from suffering altogether.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I feel, it feels a bit daunting for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I'm kind of satisfied with sort of halfway.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, you will take responsibility for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, when the other half of suffering that you haven't freed yourself, comes your way, you won't be blaming others, you won't be resorting to ill will, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: Psychologizing your suffering, finding excuses for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You'll accept it as part of the deal that you accepted when you clarified your perspective and your goals.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you haven't done that, everything will always be someone else's fault and you're not going to be responsible for anything you do, yet you're going to be equally bound, even more probably, with suffering and you won't be able to do anything about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means your efforts are completely misdirected, yet that was the goal from the start.
[SPEAKER_01]: And now, for somebody who does practice dhamma, just, again, ask yourself, well, why am I practicing dhamma?
[SPEAKER_01]: To be free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, is my current way of practicing, is it contributing?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, I hope it is, but do you know for sure that it is?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it must.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's not the right answer.
[SPEAKER_01]: It must be contributing, because I've been doing it for 20 years.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's contributing, it means your suffering is lessening.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means possibility to suffer is being lessened, fading out.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to be honest and admit, because the answer might not be a pleasing one.
[SPEAKER_01]: Especially if you invested 20 years in practice, and you still can't tell whether you're anything closer to being free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, that is an absolutely necessary step.
[SPEAKER_01]: For as long as you ignore to address it in such a direct, non-compromising manner, you can be practicing for hundreds of years, and still remain a putu jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: And sometimes, all it would take for you to stop being puthujjana is that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just admit that you are puthujjana.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't... like... because some people might have actually done the right practice, but they don't know it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they can only find out once they admit that they don't know it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, if it were right, their efforts, their reflection, then they'd... oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But because they are too afraid to go that way, they'll never find out.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why they won't be a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why it's a great loss.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, all your efforts remain undermined just by lacking that last grain of courage.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just admitting to yourself that you don't know, truly, on that existential level.
[SPEAKER_00]: After so many years of practice, of so-called practice, of trying to...
[SPEAKER_00]: I suppose, like, someone trying to get rich and then pretending that they are already rich after ten years.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, pretty much, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is, again, it's another discrepancy.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, arahant is completely, hundred percent discrepancy-free.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any discrepancy in the existential is impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a definition of an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you start recognizing that, you would see exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I'm, I'm, I'm, I'm practicing, or I'll say, I'm, I'm, I'm, I'm working to be rich, but I'm not rich
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I can be blaming others, or I can accept others as a factor in me not being rich, and then incorporate it in my efforts, and then upgrade my efforts.
[SPEAKER_01]: But only once I admit that I'm poor.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't admit it, it will be everybody else's fault, that's preventing you from getting there, or whatever, and you're still going to be doing the same things, because of which you're not getting where you want to get.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you won't be questioning your efforts of getting rich, acquiring wealth, despite your immediate poverty.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, is there like a time period that one could say, you could try a certain... Well, that's what... we go back to the very first thing we were talking about, the faith.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to have some faith, and you have to give it some time.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, yeah, after a while, you might even have to cut your losses and just restart.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're not doing it for the sake of doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're doing it to be free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're doing it for the gold.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're doing it for the fruit.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're doing it to arrive at that degree of liberation.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, obviously, somewhere down the line, for some people, that kind of got pushed in the background.
[SPEAKER_01]: And now, they became too precious, too protective of the efforts they invested in their practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Despite the lack of result.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then they defend that.
[SPEAKER_01]: They defend that kind of indefensible position, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a contradiction.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they say, well, I might not be a sotāpanna, but surely all this effort could not have been wasted.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they refuse to let go of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then...
[SPEAKER_01]: But that means they have to keep doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if they change their effort, that would be almost like the affirmation, the fact that they've been wasting... that they've been misguided and misdirecting their efforts.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, they have to stick to it, just to keep validating it for themselves that they are not wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: And because of that, they get becoming more and more wrong with each time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that... that transparency, if it were there to begin with, got completely obscured.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, question yourself and be honest.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't fabricate, don't push for answers.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just be honest.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, where am I at in my practice?
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I complacent?
[SPEAKER_01]: Do I think I have time?
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, how long will I live?
[SPEAKER_01]: All these things.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you read the suttas, that's all the time you're talking about.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you don't do it for some sort of gaining some sort of emotional kind of uplifting.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you're doing it for understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're doing it to develop clarity, to maintain perspective, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you're doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And same again.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is like from the point of view of practicing the Dhamma and the Buddha's teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even if you just want to live a wholesome, skillful life as a, you know, a normal lay person, not interested in some
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, renouncing the world that has family and job, still, it's gonna help you.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's certainly gonna strengthen you and develop your mind to deal with anything else that comes your way in the lay life.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there are a lot of things coming people's way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Lots of pressure, lots of stress, lots of burden.
[SPEAKER_01]: Initial responses, you just deal by any means necessary.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you start dealing it rightly, through the right perspective, restraint and virtue, it's going to make things more difficult in the beginning.
[SPEAKER_01]: But in the long run, it just creates this resilience that nothing else can match.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the definition of wisdom, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, you can have it to different degrees, but... Having perspective on yourself in a situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not just being absorbed and pulled by the immediacy of a situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: And which usually results in being quite reactionary.
[SPEAKER_01]: Situations like this, I react like this, just like an animal.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's also useful before.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like if people...
[SPEAKER_01]: The sooner people start thinking like this, better.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in thinking in terms of self-reflecting and really questioning themselves all the time.
[SPEAKER_01]: The sooner the better, because you would have committed less in life, as in started a family and now you have people there to look after and so on, that you can't just turn your back on.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even then, it's not too late, because there is no end to a human proliferation in the world, to the proliferation of sensuality and the wrong view and lack of restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no end to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only end to that is self-reflection.
[SPEAKER_01]: They will then prevent you from proliferating carelessly.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's true protection, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_01]: It is.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't...
[SPEAKER_01]: Taking up responsibility is a true protection.
Yeah.
For yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Getting into a group or a certain nationality or identity... That's the opposite.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's the opposite.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's when you have already disowned your responsibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you find affirmation in that act by identifying with a greater group.
[SPEAKER_01]: That just obscures it even further.
[SPEAKER_01]: The fact that you already covered up your personal responsibility for your personal existence and your personal choices.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, it's just intoxicating.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's like the masses, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even things that you wouldn't have necessarily done on a personal level, if you were with yourself, questioning yourself, you would have... you do it in a group.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, again, it just got all absorbed in this impersonal they, as Heidegger would have been talking about.
[SPEAKER_01]: That now is just acting as this complete protection and you can do whatever you want.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's like mob, definition of a mob mentality.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you know these things are wrong and you wouldn't have done them if you were on your own or with somebody else who is not like...
[SPEAKER_01]: But now, it's just... mob is intoxicated.
[SPEAKER_01]: And why it's intoxicating?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's just extension of complete lack of... well, of complete cover-up of your personal responsibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you just do stuff that you were not supposed to for their very sake.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's going to be quite inviting to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hey, let's smash these windows and break this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not because they've done anything to us or I have any gain.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just because you're not supposed to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you do it, you'll be responsible for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But now we're in a mob.
[SPEAKER_01]: Who cares?
[SPEAKER_01]: They can't get me.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's like the ultimate non-restraint, and the ultimate contradiction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you can't really... you can only cover up responsibility, which means through every single act of covering up your personal responsibility, you reaffirm that personal responsibility, because that's the very reason of your actions of covering it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, a sātra would define it as bad faith, or inauthenticity.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you carry it, you carry it in the heart of everything you do.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's almost like, if you want to make your society strong, you have to do your work.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, society will be...
[SPEAKER_01]: The strong society would be a result of personally developed individuals.
[SPEAKER_01]: Developed in a sense of accepting responsibility and gaining perspective on account of it, as in developing wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: The result would be a strong society, a resilient society, a just society.
[SPEAKER_01]: Society that has a right perspective on things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Society that's quite aligned with good is good and bad is bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's that contradiction on the existential level that's bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why bad things are bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if now, through your own self, not through adopting like dhamma or Christianity or anything, just through that self-reflection of not tolerating existential contradiction, not covering up your responsibility for your own choices,
[SPEAKER_01]: Maintaining perspective through constant self-questioning, basically, that will already result in you aligning yourself with good action.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you don't necessarily know it or have have not accepted it as some sort of external set of values.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, if everybody were to start doing that to respective degree, as much as they're capable, it will reflect on the society as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there's no society without individuals.
[SPEAKER_01]: Individuals precede society.
[SPEAKER_01]: But obviously, it's much more inspiring, so to speak, and it certainly requires less work to just identify with the impersonal notion of society.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by doing so, enable yourself even further to cover up your own responsibility that you have been avoiding.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you were transparent to begin with, you wouldn't have identified yourself, because you realize what a contradiction that is.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't be they.
[SPEAKER_01]: No matter how much you're absorbed in a in a greater cause and whatnot, you cannot step outside of your point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ever.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're completely confined to that perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, you say, no, this is not me, this is a greater good, this is a greater service, this is a greater group, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you really want to contribute to a group, you do so from the inside, as in every single individual.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't abstract the group as if it's independent of individuals.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's basically an attempt at a shortcut.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hey, let's create a philosophy or a policy or a political system that would be dealing with group as such, putting individuals second.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that was the definition of communism, or certainly one of the principles, maybe not the definition.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's like, okay, well, you theorized the perfection of a group,
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you try.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in order to maintain this perfect image of a group, we'll be sort of attacking individuals and dealing with them, because we want to... And all you're doing is maintaining your own notion, your own perspective, what you think group is.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't step outside of your personal point of view, ever.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you do, it's in order to cover it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence the group identity, group politics, and mob mentality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nationalism, anything, religion, if it's done for those reasons, and it is, usually.
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't be stepping outside of your group if you're not running away from your own self, self-responsibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't need a group.
[SPEAKER_00]: I wonder how society would look if everyone took personal responsibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, as I said, it would be, it would probably be much, much more aligned with principles of good and principles of bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: People would have that on... on an average, sort of... an average person would have a good... would have a good sort of judgment of what's good, what's bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, like, he would have a notion of it, why good is good, bad is bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you could see how modern society, how far it's removed from that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, people would know and value certain things, but that's far from having... having... that's far from saying that they understood those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Buddha was talking about the just leader back in the day, the righteous king.
[SPEAKER_01]: Clearly, he's developed knowledge of good is good, bad is bad, and then he wouldn't be just taking and conquering, be giving back.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, people can have a certain certain quality to their life, not just exploitation for the sake of personal gain.
[SPEAKER_01]: And because of that, then people start valuing that, and then they start doing the same, because the king is just, they are the just ones.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they don't blame you gratuitously or try to avoid their own responsibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, basically, that's how people already are acting, responsibly and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you would really stand out.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a decline of society, basically, when sensuality and avoiding of responsibility become a norm.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you realize that, like in schools, for example, when you were growing up, when I was growing up, I mean, we were taught everything and nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But,
[SPEAKER_01]: Has any of us ever been taught in our schools, elementary or higher, like, you know, the value of patience, the value of sense restraint, the value of being able to say no to yourself, to be... No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything...
[SPEAKER_01]: If you got any of that, it was circumstantial.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I think it's quite universal.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't think... like the whole notion of school, back in, you know, the days of the ancient Greece, was to part... sort of to enable people to go through their life more wisely, to be able to deal, to basically to create a perspective for them, they will then create in a better life for them.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you realize today, there's none of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Perspective?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're just being thrown information by the teacher,
[SPEAKER_01]: If you peddle the information back, you're passed.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't, very little understanding of it is actually encouraged.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because people who are teaching haven't understood it themselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're just going through a curriculum.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, you can't be surprised that then the value on the level of society is just a mirroring personal values, which is just following your desires, getting what you want whenever you want it, however you want it, not being responsible, blaming others.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's kind of a norm nowadays.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's impossible, the perfect society.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's impossible, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The perfect society would be basically a saṅgha of arahants, but there wouldn't be a society anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: That doesn't mean, of course, that a person should not be aiming at perfection internally, personally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because aiming at 100% will at least mirror 20% into society of good, that then other people can learn from.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not the goal, it's not to perfect society.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, that would be... Basically, like, think of society as a... as like a generated image on account of operating individuals.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's that operation of those individuals, their actions, that's the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: Generating image of it is just a symptom of a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you could see the... you could basically see the problems of individuals by looking at the problems of society.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would just be a more general projection of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: By you trying to deal with the problems of society and the level of society, it's like trying to deal with the projection of a problem, not the actual problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's... you can use it to learn from it, to maintain perspective, but the problem is undone on the personal level, through that responsibility and self-reflection, and questioning, and natural virtue that will come out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, the projection will change.
[SPEAKER_01]: You'll be projecting those things, not the lack of those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's replace this kind of arrangement of society with another arrangement, with a different system.
[SPEAKER_01]: But again, that's missing the point.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just basically fighting over types of projection.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or trying... fighting over ways you should be dealing with projections.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you're not uprooting the actual problem that is being projected.
[SPEAKER_01]: And again, that attitude itself is a projection of the individual attitude towards your own problems.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, when people suffer, when people experience difficulties, they don't necessarily look into themselves as in, is this a projection of my attitude or my actions?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: They want to manage it.
[SPEAKER_01]: They want to manage the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: They want to remove the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: They want to get rid of the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything on the level of society is a projection of the... from the level of individuals, whichever prevails.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that in itself is already a projection of the individual attitude that they have... that people have in regard to their own problems and suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I have a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, who caused it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, if it's me, okay, well, then I'll either apologize or let's pretend it never happened.
[SPEAKER_01]: All these things are management of the problem that has already arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you can do that, but that's not uprooting the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't confuse the two.
[SPEAKER_01]: Uprooting of the problem is then reflecting further and saying, okay, but will I in the future then cause the same issue for myself through my careless actions, for example?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or will I be able to prevent it?
[SPEAKER_01]: How can I prevent it?
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's a true definition of learning from your own mistakes, like trial and error, where you want to look beyond, not just to deal with this particular issue that has arisen, but to basically extrapolate a principle that you can discern, that can then help you not make the same mistake in the future.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if that's your attitude towards your own personal existence and actions and responsibility and choices and so on, and that's the attitude of other people as well, that will be reflected in society then.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or at least not the largest society, but your family.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, of course, yeah, yeah, certainly, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Individual, then the family, then the smaller group, whatever, then obviously.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, but it all trickles down, like a, like a, like a stream on a mountaintop.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's filling down lower streams, that are filling down lower rivers, that are filling down lower lakes, and other rivers, and then eventually filling down the seas, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you dry it up at the top, or if you remove the pollution from it at the top, eventually, even the sea will cease to be polluted.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, if you're just trying to deal with the level of... on the level of the sea, without addressing the source of the pollution, well, you're fighting a losing battle.